[Music]
so Lina thank you for joining me welcome
pleasure so we're putting out a whole
series of films this week on what Jordan
Peterson's relationship to the left and
Jordan Peterson's relationship to I mean
the left is a quite broad term and for
me it also covers most people on the
more progressive end of the spectrum and
I know that you've got a real interest
in the developmental society although
sort of shared interests on how we move
towards a sort of more integration of
left and right so I'm not sort of just
begging you as someone on the left but
you're you would you agree that you're
more on the progressive end of society
no I think I'm in the middle and I tried
to make my spectrum as before and wide
and deep and with as many aspirations as
possible and I see a deep value in all
the democratic fractions that have had
so so I really try to see the full
spectrum and I think that is that is the
future what do you personally find
valuable in Jordan Peterson I find it
very valuable that he has given a more
complex understanding of the
conservative and the liberal even I
think his liberal version should be
divided and should be more nuanced and
he has brought a lot of academic
knowledge and history and theology and
psychology into the public sphere and
into our conversation in society and it
has been almost impossible to bring
these topics into the broader debate the
broader conversation so I mean that's
really great I did love it because it
means that we can talk about some things
now for which we did not share
vocabulary before and that is really
important and I also think and that is
why I Illustrated it like this is that I
mean if you up here I have absolute
control and down here have absolute
chaos order and Kay
this is the axis that the journey
Peterson is talking about
I mean libertarianism with outing
acceptance of all the other ideologies
and of society will turn the world into
chaos on the other hand if the
Conservatives or the Socialists gain
absolute control and order it will be to
tell at Arianism all right I think that
axis between order and chaos is really
is really a good tool and that is
inspired a lot hmm
I was gonna ask how your perspective has
it changed your perspective on the world
in any way no and one of the reasons is
that many of the things that you have a
background in economy and theology I
never completed in my theology studies
so I know most of the mythology's that
you talk that he talks about so so
they're not new to me I see them perhaps
in a slightly different light I also see
some things that he that he is
completely missing particularly when it
comes to this whole thing about the
patriarchy and the order in chaos and
even parts of chaos and men know where
the force of order I think both sexes
both genders contribute with order and
chaos I don't think he defined it as men
and women being ordering chaos he'd say
the masculine principle yes
undifferentiated in some way does map
onto Taoism and Buddhism when you see
illustrations I mean there's the father
standing for order and hero the son
being the creative I think he calls it
the creative hero who is the one who can
transform the existing society into the
next order of things that the next kind
of society and a more complex society
they are men and the force of chaos has
portrayed us as the big mother so
she's usually a woman so so there is but
yes the masculine and the feminine but
if you look at the and this is where I
think he has this is really big blind
spot which is that all in the history
that he is describing and interpreting
and bringing into order it's just the
written history so it's the history and
the mythology's of the Bronze Age Iron
Age and modernity you can evil times and
the Renaissance but but it's it's the
written history and what's interesting
about the written history from the dawn
of picture racketing and particularly
alphabet is that this coincides with
bronze and iron it coincides with the
axial age the big trade route between
China and reason Italy so that axis
geographical axis and the same planet so
and the first really big empires but
before that there was still managed
active culture which had a mother
goddess and that I was probably about
fifteen thousand years of Stone Age
agriculture maybe was just ten experts
or debating right now and before that
that was hunter-gather stone age so join
me Peterson completely misses the
animism of the hunter-gatherers and the
mother earth goddess of the early
farmers at least as far as will have
come in his maps of meaning I'm still I
still have like sixty pages left there
may be stuff that he that he hasn't
talked about yet but I got it so what
the the mythology is that here analyzing
and referring to are from the Bronze Age
and Iron Age which is also the age of
the patriarchy because when you live in
an together
group of maybe maximum two hundred
people it's rather egalitarian you don't
have to keep order it by using violence
if you live in a village
Stone Age agriculture maybe it's a
thousand people so yeah I have to use a
bit of violence to keep the unruly
particularly young men common and make
them behave but you don't have to build
a hierarchy and so that is also the time
span of the mother earth goddess and
were the early farmers they were really
I mean they how the you know the plants
come up from the ground that's the
mother earth giving birth so she was the
organizing principle but then when you
get into the Bronze Age and Iron Age and
you have some of these cities 3,000
years ago with hello 100,000 people at
least 10,000 people you get a different
very different kind of power and that is
also where male chauvinism begins you
can read from the texts so so the
epistemology the frame of reference
within which during be Peterson is
working is only part of our history and
it's a part of our history where yes the
men struggled to create order in these
big societies and the way that they
could do it was through religion through
narrative through force through violence
and the women became part of their
property and so you also have the manly
going out to war should have them
traveling for trade so you had men who
travel from city to city or from village
to village and when you travel you have
to be able to say I'm so-and-so coming
from this place who are you ego sheet
and that creates a consciousness and
awareness that you don't get if you are
just stuck on the home with the children
and all the chicken and all the goats
and you have you're not allowed to go
out on your own because you're well man
there's a risk of rape and there's a
risk of attack sure there are all kinds
of risks to women in these societies and
so who ended up writing the mythology's
well the man once you can see beyond
that and see what came before that you
get a much richer perspective on who we
are as as a civilization and it's a
complex thing but but he does defend
Western culture
does defend the hierarchies of
competence so you know in a way he does
defend the system that some people are
calling a patriarchy hey my nice where I
kind of align with what you're saying as
well is that I do think that he that
it's altogether possible that what we're
experiencing now is a shift from a sort
of male way of looking at the world to a
way of looking at the world that
incorporates the feminine and I think
his his main focus is on reviving the
reviving the masculine power of the
culture and and actually I think that's
necessary but it's potentially not
sufficient and what we actually is a is
a reinvigoration of the divine masculine
if you want to see that but also for it
to be match with the divine feminine
we've created a society where physical
strength is no longer the defining thing
we would hope so potentially the
potential for genuine equality and
genuine both both men and women
connecting with their more so intuitive
direct ways of knowing if there's a
potential for that it would seem so yeah
I think that within within the within
the known structures and epistemology of
Western tradition
Jordan B Peterson is doing a really good
job and the irony is that in maps of
meaning he says that if you insist on
staying remaining with the old
understanding of the world as the world
changes then you are evil and what I
don't see Jordan B Peters in doing is
taking that step outside the known
epistemology becoming a creative hero
struggling with the big big horrible
chaotic mother and then coming back and
sharing with us what the next
epistemology should look like what is
the next mythology what is the next
organization of society and exactly how
do we get both the male and the female
integral
into a meaningful culture and meaningful
civilization and we do have an enormous
young man problem because everything
that young men burger I mean everything
that evolution made out of young men
that which is let me say that which is
unique to young and are things that we
don't really need anymore
you don't allow anybody to have any
dangers and everything more and and in
some respects thank God for that because
it's a much more civilized peaceful
society but it also means that there's
this face where where young men are
suffering and I think that Jordan P
Peterson there's addressing that and
that's a very very important group that
we are not helping there's a lot of
debate and especially in progressive
circles as to where the Jordan Peterson
is a positive or a negative net
influence and a lot of people come down
on the side that he's a negative
influence what's your view oh no no I
totally disagree Larry I think he's a
very positive influence because he's
voicing something that we have not been
able to voice in very long time and that
is important at most we must have that
as part of who we are and he gives it
you give to the very well founded and
well researched voice I mean the
post-modernism is a transition face you
cannot build societies on post - why
can't you build that society and post
modernism well because post modernism is
about deconstruction and you cannot
build structures on deconstruction so
there are really important insights from
post modernism because there's a
deconstruction and there's relativizing
everything and the ability to switch
perspectives and seeing seeing your own
culture with the perspective of
everybody else
we just need to combine that with all
the other phases that we've been going
through when you need to combine this
post-modernism with with modernity we
need the signs of modernity and
as peterson have pointed out which is
really really crucial
we need the narratives and the stories
and the ethical moral struggles
existential struggles of pre modernity
of this whole face of written history
because they were people just like us so
there's a poetic world and a symbolic
world that touches us in a different way
and has things to say that science
cannot say because it is not what
science does what can guide us is wisdom
and human experience and moral values
and and bringing that back into the
public debate is a really big
contribution and then before the
pre-modern or traditional written
history iron and Bronze Age society
there was all the Stone Age indigenous
culture which has a spirituality and a
sense of intimate connectedness that you
can only happen if you're in small
groups and then we have them Derna tea
and science that both are really really
crucial if we're to have democracy
functioning States electricity we've had
a bit of a technical problem with the
connection here I mean we wouldn't even
have had a connection if it hadn't been
for modern science so so there are all
these things that are equally important
but in each their time each each they're
placed